

ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE EXPERT Leuven, Belgium

💌 axel.faes@gmail.com | 🌴 theaxec.github.io | 🖸 TheAxeC | 🛅 axelfaes | 🗲 Scholar | 🏛 KULeuven Who's Who

## Abstract

I am a Msc. Artificial Intelligence and Msc. Computer Science Engineering student at KU Leuven. My main interests include algebraic effect handlers, program optimization, type systems, graph theory, artificial intelligence, neural computing and brain-computer interfaces. I am participating in the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track) at KU Leuven. I am also a big supporter of Open Source Software.

## Research Interests \_\_\_\_

**Programming Language Theory** Algebraic Effect Handlers, Type Systems and Program Optimization **Artifical Intelligence** Machine Learning, Reinforcement Learning and Virtual Reality

**Neuroscience** Neural Computing and Brain Computer Interfaces

# **Educational background**

Advanced Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Artificial Intelligence

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2018

Engineering and Computer Science

Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Computer Science (Burgelijk Ingenieur - ir.)

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2016 - Jul. 2018

KUTEUVEN Artificial Intelligence & Theoretical Computer Science

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Science (79% - Magna Cum Laude)

Hasselt, Belgium

Physics and General courses

UHASSELT

Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2016

Business Summer School: United in Manchester (0739)

Manchester, UK

THE UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

International Business

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

# Honors & Awards

Oct. 2017 Honoursprogramme, of the Faculty of Engineering Science

KU Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2017 3rd place, ICFP 2017 Student Research Competition

Oxford, UK

Jul. 2016 Bachelor Award, in Computer Science

UHasselt, Belgium

May. 2016 3rd place, ACM CHI 2016 Student Design Competition (Interaction Design and User Experience.)

San Jose, CA, USA

Feb. 2016 **2nd place**, BeGDC (Belgian Game Development Championship)

Brussel, Belgium

Jan. 2016 IELTS, Academic Module (8.0/9.0)

Brussel, Belgium

# Work & Research Experience

## **Student Job: Creating System Identification course**

KU LEUVEN

Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2017 - Current

- · Faculty of Engineering Science: ESAT (Electrical Engineering)
- Research group: STADIUS

### Research Assistant: design of type-&-effect system for Eff based on row polymorphism

Leuven, Belgium Apr. 2017 - Oct. 2017

KU LEUVEN

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track).
- Topic: Development of an row-based type-&-effect system for the Eff programming language

AXEL FAES · CURRICULUM VITAE **DECEMBER 15, 2017** 

KU Leuven Sep. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- · Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track). My project is part of the C1 project: Algebraic Effect Handlers: Harnessing the Fundamental Power of Effects. Eff is a functional programming language that uses handlers to handle all kinds of effects. These effects could be I/O, exceptions, user-defined, etc. My task is to design, implement, benchmark and formally proof new optimisations in the Eff compiler. The compiler is written in OCaml.

#### Web performance research intern

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Jul. 2016 - Sep. 2016

- I worked on the iMinds PRO-FLOW project.
- My work involved creating multiple usecases to measure website performance. The main focus is on the difference between the http versions (http1.1, https, http2).
- During the project, I had to utilise multiple servers, maintain and extend the nodejs framework used to measure website performance, and manually optimize commercial websites using PHP, JS, HTML and CSS.

#### **Summer Internship Physical Computing**

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Aug. 2015 - Sep. 2015

Work on a project which focuses on the interaction between a human entity and a drone, aswell as interaction between the drone and virtual
objects. This project is written in C++, used the Optitrack motion capture and a custom created drone.

# **Extracurricular Activities**

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE

Sep. 2017 - Current

- POC of Master Computer Science Engineering
- POC of Advanced Master Artificial Intelligence
- Member of Departmental council of Computer Science
- Member of Department board of Computer Science
- Member of Faculty council of Engineering Science

CoderDojo Belgium Uasselt, PXL

COACH Sep. 2014 - Current

• Teach children how to program utilising Scratch, Python, Minecraft and Lego mindstorm.

Student Council UHasselt

Member Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

- Member of Board of Education
- Member of Faculty Council
- Member of Board of Student Facilities
- Member of Diversity Commission
- Temporary representative in VVS (Vlaamse Vereniging van Studenten vzw)

Student Council UHasselt

Мемвеr Маг. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- Member of Board of Education
- Member of Faculty Council
- Member of Board of Student Facilities

**UHAsselt**Hasselt, Belgium

Student Representative Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2016

- Representing students interests in a Computer Science education context.
- · This meant discussing with the university in order to improve teaching, learning, assessment and academic services.
- Representing Computer Science education for high school students

# Natural Languages\_

English Fluent (IELTS: 8.0/9.0)

Dutch Mothertongue

French Basic Knowledge

# Projects\_\_\_\_\_

#### **Software Architecture course - Project**

Leuven, Belgium

Developer Feb. 2017 - Jul. 2017

Project made for the course 'Software Architecture'. The goal was to design a software architecture in UML for a IoT-platform concerning pluggable sensors. The platform allows storage of customer data and the use of third party applications for data analytics. Final score - 18/20

#### ICAL parser for KU Leuven schedules

Leuven, Belgium

LEAD DEVELOPER

Aug. 2016 - Current

An nodejs application to create an iCalender file for courses at KU Leuven. Allows the creation of a schedule containing courses from different
masters and the option to ignore events.

#### Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems

Hasselt, Belgium

BACHELOR'S THESIS

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• The thesis gives an overview of how machine learning algorithms could be used for intrusion detection using only IP Flows. The system has been used to detect intrusions in Cegeka Hasselt Datacenter network.

### **Software engineering: Search and Recommendation System**

Hasselt, Belgium

TEAM MEMBER

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

A search and recommendation system for VoD (Video on Demand) for Androme. The system is currently being used in production in the Nebula
project. Both Content-Based Recommendations and Collaborative filtering techniques were implemented. Made in a team of 5 (Pieter Teunen,
Luuk Raaijmakers, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski, Wouter Bollaert) utilising Java and the Spring framework. Final score - 15/20

TTUI: Household Survival Hasselt, Belgium

Researcher

- Project made for the class 'Technologies and Tools for User Interfaces'.
- A tower-defense style game written in Unity utilising Optitrack motion capture. The game combines the virtual world and reality, by allowing
  users to interact with the virtual world using real-world objects. Made by Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski. Final score 18/20

### Cardinal: scripting language

Hasselt, Belgium

Sep. 2015 - Dec. 2015

LEAD DEVELOPER

Jan. 2015 - Sep. 2015

- Cardinal is a small, fast, class-based, Object Oriented scripting language written in C. It is built upon the skeleton of an existing scripting language and shows how I can modify and improve existing software, as well as design new components to this software.
- · New components include a debugger, an embedding API, multiple inheritance and a new module system.

United in Manchester Manchester, UK

TEAM LEADER

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

• A summer school which focuses on teamwork in cross-cultural and multidisciplinary teams, global product development and entrepreneurship. Our team developed a start-up idea on Food Management/Delivery system. Product pitch took place at the end of the course for feedbacks from professionals and for potential commercialisation. Our team consisted of Axel Faes, Linh Chi Evelyn Phan, Reinaert Van de Cruys and Maria Barouh.

### **PSOPV: Visual Programming IDE**

Hasselt, Belgium

DEVELOPER

Feb. 2015 - Jul. 2015

 A Visual programming IDE created by Axel Faes & Matthijs Kaminski for a course of Hasselt University. The purpose of the IDE is to create 'black boxes' which can send events (signals packed with data) to eachother. We take the idea of using drag-able blocks in a visual IDE and expand on it. Final score - 17/20

## **Publications**

#### CONFERENCE PAPERS

Robin Marx, Peter Quax, Axel Faes and Wim Lamotte, "Concatenation, embedding and sharding: Do HTTP/1 performance best

[1] practices make sense in HTTP/2?", WEBIST 2017 - Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies.

#### **EXTENDED ABSTRACTS**

Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers, "Towards a core language with row-based effects for optimised compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.

Kashyap Todi, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski, "Purpose-Centric Appropriation of Everyday Objects as Game

[3] Controllers", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Late Breaking Work.

Kashyap Todi, Donald Degraen, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski and Kris Luyten, "Household Survival:

[4] Immersive Room-Sized Gaming Using Everyday Objects as Weapons", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Student Game Competition.

## **THESIS**

[5] **Axel Faes**, "Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems", Bachelor's thesis 2016.

## **POSTERS**

Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers, "Towards a core language with row-based effects for optimised compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.

## TALKS, PRESENTATIONS AND OTHER MEDIA

Sep. 19, 2017	"Honours student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in ACM SIGPLAN", KU Leuven, Department of
	Computer Science.

Sep. 19, 2017 "Student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in the ACM SIGPLAN Student Research Competition in ICFP conference", KU Leuven, Department of Computer Science, DTAI.